<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The commendation of cockes, and cock-fighting VVherein is shewed, that cocke-fighting was before the comming of Christ.</title>
            <author>Wilson, George, fl. 1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847077</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12087</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12087)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 724:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The commendation of cockes, and cock-fighting VVherein is shewed, that cocke-fighting was before the comming of Christ.</title>
                  <author>Wilson, George, fl. 1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Purfoot] for Henrie Tomes, and are to be sold at his shop ouer against Graies Inne gate in Holburne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: George VVilson.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cockfighting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12087:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12087:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Commendation of Cockes, and Cock-fighting. Wherein is ſhewed, that <hi>Cocke-fighting was before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henrie Tomes,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Graies Inne gate in Holburne, 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12087:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12087:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir <hi>Henrie Bedingfield</hi> in <hi>the Countie of Norffolke Knight:</hi> George Wilſon <hi>wiſheth in this world, health,</hi> wealth, and proſperitie: and in the world to come, eternall felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatiſe (right Worſhipfull) tending to the commendation of Cockes, and Cocke-fighting, was by me long ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in <hi>London, Boſtone,</hi> and other places: but like an ill Debtor, I haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken many dayes of payment: yet now at the laſt I haue made perfourmance, although perchance not altogether in ſuch good manner, as ſome men may expect, yet is it in the beſt ſort that I can: and as it is, I hope you will accept it. <hi>Miſon</hi> could not paint ſo exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely, as <hi>Apelles</hi> did, yet <hi>Darius</hi> allowed of his labours. Silly <hi>Baucis</hi> could not feaſt <hi>Iupiter</hi> in ſiluer plate, but in wodden veſſels. All that honour <hi>Eſculape,</hi> cannot decke his ſhrine with Iewels: neither can all they that write, expreſſe their mindes, ſo well as they would. But as <hi>Apollo</hi> gaue Oracles, as well to the poore man for his mite, as to the rich man for his million: ſo I doubt not, but your worſhip will accept of this my poore offering, and patronize this booke as willingly, as I dedicate it har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily,
<pb facs="tcp:12087:3"/> and although I know it is vnworthy, to weare your worthy name: yet haue I (preſuming on your wonted curteſie) placed it on the browe of it, to be an ornament vnto it to grace it, and a ſhield to defend it, againſt all enuious detractors. Now, the reaſon why I haue made choyſe of you, rather than of any other, is, both in regard of the good will you beare to Cocke-fighting, (wherein I know you take exceeding great delight) and alſo to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt my loue, and dutie vnto your worſhip, to whom I am more than much beholding, for many and moſt vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued curteſies. Being loath to trouble you with too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous an Epiſtle, in all humility, commending my booke to your fauourable protection, I end, hoping one day to doe ſomething that ſhalbe more worthy of your acceptance, till when and euer, I reſt your Worſhips, to commaund.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12087:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader whoſoeuer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, in regard that I haue alwayes been greatly affectioned to the moſt pleaſant ſport of Cock-figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I haue thought good to ſhewe vnto thee (in this following treatiſe) the excellent nature, rare qualities, ſtout courage, vndaunted reſolution, and the moſt admirable vertues, that are in fighting Cockes, and withall to diſcribe, and ſhew forth the manner, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and good order that is obſerued and vſed in the pleaſing paſtime of Cock-fighting, with a briefe repetition of the high commendations that learned writers, and mighty princes, as <hi>Themiſtocles, Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch, Plinie, Caeſar, Marke Anthony,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great perſonages haue giuen vnto them, not onely to ſatisfie and pleaſe mine owne humor ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but to fulfill the earneſt requeſt and expectation of diuers men of great account, who haue longe time labored with me, &amp; often incited me to doe it. Wherfore conſidering with my ſelfe, that although many men in this Realme, hold it in moſt high eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, yet there are not, nor haue been any, that euer gaue it any publike commendation. I thought good to ſhew my ſimple skill in the diſcribing of
<pb facs="tcp:12087:4"/> it; which deſcription although it be farre inferiour to the worthineſſe of my ſubiect: yet I intreat thee to accept it kindely, or elſe to amend it quickely: but if thou wilt neither accept of it, nor amend it, but ſcorne my worke, and contemne mee for my good will, then the care is taken: and I am conſtant in my reſolution. Thus kindly commending both my ſelfe and my Booke, to the curteſie of all cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Readers, I bid thee farewell. From <hi>Wretton</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Noffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in what he may, G. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12087:4"/>
            <head>The Commendation of Cockes, <hi>and Cocke-fighting.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is written in the firſt Chapter</hi> of the firſt Booke of <hi>Moſes,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Geneſis:</hi> that God gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, Soueraigntie, Rule, &amp; Dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer the fiſhes in the ſea; ouer the fowles of the aire; and ouer euery liuing thing that he had made: and behold, it was excéeding good, and was appointed vnto man for to doe him homage, and to ſerue him in all places, and times, in his ſeuerall and neceſſary vſes and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for clothing and ſuſtenance for his bodie; but alſo for recreation and paſtime, to delight his minde: as with Cocke-fighting, Hawking, Hunting, and ſuch like. For honeſt recreation is not prohibited by the word of God: but rather tollerated and allowed.</p>
               <p>The Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> rehearſing the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous workes of the Almighty, in the 104 <hi>Pſalme,</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking of the ſea; there goe the ſhips, and there is that <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> whom thou haſt made to take his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime therein. Now if the fiſh be admitted to take their
<pb facs="tcp:12087:5"/> paſtime in the ſea, and the foules to ſport them in the aire? How much more may man (which is the king of Creatures) take his pleaſure vpon the earth? for our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, you are of more worth, then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sparrowes. And the wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> verifieth, that this is the portion of a man vnder the ſunne, to eate, and to drinke, and to make his heart merrie with the moderate vſe of the good creatures of God.</p>
               <p>Diuers other places in the Holy Scriptures, tending to this effect, might be alleaged, to proue and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the lawfulneſſe of mirth and modeſt paſtime: which in all ages, and in all places whatſoeuer, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies bene both tollerated, and commended: but I will omit the recitall of them, and proceede in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended deſcription of Cockes, and Cocke-fighting: which pleaſant, and delightfull ſport, is ſo excellent of it ſelfe, that it meriteth much praiſe; and ſo auncient, that it may eaſily be prooued: it was vſed long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour Chriſts peregrination: for doe but looke into <hi>Plutarchs</hi> Bookes, called the liues of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, and you ſhall find in the ſtory of <hi>M. Antonius,</hi> that the Soothſayers counſelled him to beware &amp; take héede of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> becauſe his Cockes did alwayes looſe the day, when they fought with <hi>Caeſars.</hi> And I alſo reade, that <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> that worthy, valiant and time-eternized Conqueror, when he beſieged the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and great Countrey <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> did vſe Cocke-fighting: for at his beginning, and firſt entrance into that enterprize, before he gaue any aſſault, or made any offer of batterie againſt the countrey: he commanded that two Cockes of the kind, ſhould bee brought vnto him, and be ſet downe to fight before him, in the open view of all his valiant ſouldiers, whom he earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted moſt ſeriouſly to behold and marke the battell, which was performed on both parts, with ſuch ſtout
<pb facs="tcp:12087:5"/> courage, and magnanimitie, that all the ſpectators did admire, and wonder to behold the dreadfulneſſe of their fight, the deepe indented woundes that each of them had, and in the end with what excéeding great reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> died: which bloody battell was no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ended, but <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> commanding ſilence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan this Oration.</p>
               <p>RIght worthy Gentlemen, couragious Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and my moſt valiant and louing Souldiers, it is oftentimes ſeene, that he which is leaſt able to beare, ſhall haue the greateſt burthen layd vpon his backe, as appeareth moſt apparantly by me at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, who being ordained &amp; appointed to be your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor, and the chiefe Generall of the field; whereas many of you are more worthie, and better able to haue ſupplyed my place, and diſcharged my office, than my ſelfe am. But ſince it is my Princes pleaſure, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre me to this high preheminence and great dignity, although I cannot performe all that is requiſite to be done, by a man of ſo great a commaund, in ſuch abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute manner as I gladly would: yet will I not faile to ſhew my vttermoſt endeauor to accompliſh, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieue whatſoeuer I can. Now the occaſion of this our preſent warlike preparation, is not vnknowne to you all, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> means how we ſhal bring to paſſe our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended purpoſes, is vnknowne to any, and remayneth doubtfull both to you, and to me: and therefore the better to effect what we doe intend, I thought it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, but rather moſt neceſſarie, to preſent vnto your publicke view the fierce fight, and cruell combate of theſe two (late vndaunted, but now dead) Cockes, that the ſight of the courage which they ſhewed in this quarrell, might pierce into your hearts, and make a déepe impreſſion in your diſcréet conſiderations, that
<pb facs="tcp:12087:6"/> thereby you might be the more enboldened and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, than you could haue béene by all the words of comfort that I can relate, or by all the examples of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer accidents that may be repeated. I might here take occaſion to vnfold, and ſhew vnto you the ſundrie ſhifts, and ſubtill euaſions, which they vſed in their fight, for the eſchewing of each dangerous blowe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchangeably paſſing betwixt them; but for your ſelues could not but perceiue it, I will let paſſe as a thing not materiall to be any more recyted And now only as your Director I aduiſe you, as your Captaine I councell you, and as your friend &amp; fellow ſouldier I inſtantly exhort you, to call to mind the inuincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of theſe vnreaſonable creatures: what cruelty they indured in this conflict, how many bléeding woundes they ſuſteined, neuer ſhewing ſo much as any ſigne of yéelding, no not at the very laſt gaſpe of their liues: when being not able to ſtrike, ſtand, or ſée each other, yet euen then they manifeſted their incredible valour, vntill the one was left dead with the blowes of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary, &amp; the other not able to liue, hauing obtained ſo doubtfull a victorie: and all this doubtles for no other cauſe ſo farre as I can coniecture) then for the loue of their Hens Now therfore moſt heroicall minded Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and couragious Souldiers, if theſe creatures wanting the vſe of reaſon, who are only guided by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, haue ſhewed ſuch ſtout, vndaunted and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courage for the loue of their phéeres: let not vs which are men, indued with wiſedome and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and with farre greater prerogatiues of nature, then any other inferiour creatures, they being ſubiect vnto vs, and made for our vſe: but we hauing our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures much indéered, and bettered by art, Let not vs I ſay, ſhew more cowardize and faint hearted timorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then theſe ſilly fowles of the aire haue done.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12087:6"/>
               <p>I read of many men in former times, which to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their Princes, haue entred into doubtful fraies, and moſt daungerous combats inſomuch, that ſome of them in thoſe actions, haue ended their liues by the dint of their déereſt companions ſwordes. Some haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed their dayes in trauell, and vndergone death in moſt tyrannicall maner, with great miſerie, and much extremitie for the good of their countrey, ſacking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but fame for themſelues, yet deſirous to procure profit to their natiue ſoiles. Other ſome haue ſuffered death for the intire affection which they did beare vnto their friends: diuers haue plunged themſelues into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and mighty perils for the defence of their wiues and children: and very many haue béene more willing to looſe their liues, then to looſe their lands and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall liuings: but neuer any (I thinke) hath béene ſo much ſubiect to cowardize, that they would not fight to ſaueguard their owne liues. Yet this is our cauſe now, nay our cauſe is more then ſo, to animate vs vnto this conflict: for we are commanded by our Prince (whom of neceſſitie wee muſt obey) and challenged by our mortall enemies, who ſéeke the death of our Prince: the ſpeedy ſubuerſion, and vtter ouerthrow of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Countrey, the ranſacking of our ſubſtance, the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of our virgins, the rauiſhing of our wiues, and laſtly, the moſt bloody Maſſacre of all our children and friends: reſeruing our ſelues, to indure ſome extreame and intollerable tortures. Therefore (I beſéech you) arme your ſelues with courage correſpondent for ſuch a conflict: and let vs chooſe and reſolue rather to die valiantly with honour, then to yéeld our ſelues coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the mercie of our mercileſſe enemies, who haue made preparation for our generall deſtruction. Theſe words <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> vttered with ſuch vehemencie of ſpirit, and with ſuch a ſhew of vndoubted valour, that
<pb facs="tcp:12087:7"/> al the whole army (which before was ſomewhat daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſcouraged with the force and multitude of their enemies) had now (by this inſtigation) ſo farre abandoned and chaſed away all former feare, that nothing could diſcourage them, for now they ſéemed to diſdaine and contemne all occaſions, which might in any ſort diſmay them: euery one thinking ſo well, and conceiuing ſuch a good opinion of their Generall, that they thought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues happie to be vnder his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and déemed euery houre to be a day long, vntill they might buckle with their boaſting aduerſaries.</p>
               <p>Whereupon they hauing made fit preparation for all their warlike prouiſion, they ſtrooke vp an Alarme, ſounded their trumpets, cornets, clarions, phifes, and other muſicall inſtruments vſed in warres, with ſuch a triumphant noyſe, as was able to haue animated an effeminate minded Souldier. And in this manner they marched couragiouſly towards their enemies, whom they aſſailed ſo fiercely with ſuch vnſpeakeable valour, that the bloody Maſſacre which they made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, (whom they ſlaughtered in great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance) was a ſufficient witneſſe to warrant their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious reſolutions, they charging them on euery ſide ſo valiantly, that the fame of that famous and heroicall acte of Chiualrie and Princely proweſſe performed in that péece of ſeruice, will neuer bee buried in obliuion ſo long as the Annalls of the Grecians remaine, or a Gréeke is liuing to record the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:12087:7"/>
               <head>Chapter. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ycurgus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law giuer of <hi>Lacedemonia,</hi> counſelled the Lacedemonians to bee both as conſtant, &amp; as couragious as a Cocke is: for this is certaine, that he is ſo conſtant to his Hennes, that he will rather die, then depart from them: and ſo couragious, that he will neuer yeeld vnto his aduerſarie, vntill death inforce him. And <hi>Plinie</hi> that famous writer ſaith, That the Cocke loueth his Hens ſo entirely, that he will take the meat out of his owne mouth, and then clucking them about him, he will beſtow it moſt liberally and kindly among them. And moreouer, if any other Cocke doe chaunce to come within his regiment, precinct, or libertie, to tread any of his Hennes, hée will ſtraight wayes encounter with his intruding aduerſarie, and valiantly aduenture his life with him, be he neuer ſo ſtrong, or ſtout, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then yéeld him any iot or part of his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Héere may all men take occaſion by this example of the Cocke, to weigh and conſider with themſelues, how louing and kinde they ought to bée vnto their wiues, and how vigilant and carefull they ſhould bée ouer them which are ſo néerely, and deerely bound vnto them by the Law of God, as to bée one fleſh, one minde, one faith, and one troth: as though both they were but one body: in which courſe, they are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Almightie, to continue vnto the end of their liues.</p>
               <p>Now this being performed (as it ought to bee) what would it doe, but worke this effect? that as in our Cockes, our wiues ſée and know, wée take exée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:12087:8"/> great pleaſure and delight: ſo it would alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, and cauſe them to ſay vnto themſelues, wée are induced and perſwaded, nay, in a manner we are euen compelled, and as it were inforced to loue our huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Cockes, and to make much of them, becauſe they doe ſhew vnto them a good and a perſwaſiue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, how they ſhould loue, regard, defend, and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh vs: for they perceiuing ſuch conſtant, faithfull, and vnfained loue, to be and remaine in vnreaſonable creatures which are onely guided and gouerned by nature, will ſurely be mooued thereby, and ſtirred vp to a farre greater loue towards vs, hauing more wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, reaſon, and vnderſtanding in themſelues, then all other kindes of liuing creatures. Now therefore, for our owne parts, we will doe this from hencefoorth, we will rather want meate our ſelues, then the Cockes ſhall: and by this meanes, we ſhall allure our huſbands to manifeſt their loue towards vs, and procure them to continue it to vs.</p>
               <p>Thus would our wiues ſay among themſelues; but to paſſe ouer that point, we read, that raſh <hi>Iſadas</hi> the Lacedemon Lord, going out naked with an hoſt of men againſt the Theban powers, in which deſperate attempted fight, he preuailed and got a great victorie. Afterwards, he being aſked why he went foorth in that maner, made this anſwers; The crauen Cock (ſaith he) had rather be couered in a roope, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come forth to fight, or if of neceſſitie he be inforced, he will ſooner run out of daunger, then endure it: but the Cocke of the Game will alwayes be forward to the fight, and neuer leaue it, for any daunger that is in it: neither will he deſire any other engine, either to defend himſelfe, or to offend his enemy, more then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame Nature hath indowed him with; and ſhall not I be as valourous as a Coeke is? Thus did <hi>Iſadas</hi> (by example of the Cocke) anſwere to
<pb facs="tcp:12087:8"/> their obiection.</p>
               <p>Now there are ſome men which will ſay, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the courage that is in our fighting Cockes, yet they are crowned but with a combe: but <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith, that nature did crowne him with a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem: and that his combe was giuen him (as indéede who can denie it) to bee an ornament to adorne him, and not (as ſome fooles thinke) to be a note of diſgrace, and ſcandall to him. <hi>Heliodorus</hi> in his <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie reporteth, that Cockes were had in ſuch great eſtimation amongſt the Egiptians, (whither <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iclea</hi> the daughter of <hi>Aſtyages</hi> the King of the Ethiops was by théeues violently carried) that both the Prieſts in <hi>Memphis,</hi> and moſt of the people which inhabited néere to the Riuer <hi>Nilus,</hi> did kéepe Cockes in their lodging-chambers, to be as an Allarum bell vnto them, to make them to be vigilant and watchfull: the one for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often wakened, they might call vpon their Idols <hi>Oſiris,</hi> and <hi>Iſis,</hi> (whom they worſhip as their God, and their Goddeſſe) and the other that they might thereby be moued to make all things ſure, and be ſtirred vp to defend themſelues againſt robbers, and theeues, by whom (in thoſe parts) they were mightily oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>Thus you may ſée that euen amongſt the heathens, Cockes were highly reſpected, and much valued, many hundreth yéeres agoe; and no doubt but they are ſo ſtill at this inſtant: and in my opinion, they deſerue, and merite more to be eſtéemed of all men, then any other fowle doth, for what fowle this day liuing in the ayre, or vpon the face of the earth, is ſo pleaſurable, and ſo profitable as the Cocke is? I confeſſe that the <hi>Arabian Phaenix</hi> is both rarer, and chaſter; but for the vſe and behoofe of man, the Cocke is farre better. In both of them hath Dame Nature done her beſt, and (to expreſſe great wonders in ſmall creatures) hath made them
<pb facs="tcp:12087:9"/> both more excellent, and more admirable, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feathered foules.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> is much prized of many, but not more prayſed of all then the Cocke is, for the one is not ſo worthy of commendations for her rareneſſe and chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (which commeth of neceſſity, becauſe there is no more of that kind) as the other is for his courage and conſtancie, who (though he hath great ſocietie) will rather die, then derogate from any of his company,</p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Michaell Drayton,</hi> an excellent Poet, now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in London, in a Booke of his called <hi>Englands He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall Epiſtles,</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> ſaith thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Arabian Bird that neuer is but one,</l>
                  <l>Is onely chaſt becauſe ſhe is alone:</l>
                  <l>But had our mother Nature made them two,</l>
                  <l>They would haue done as Doues, and Sparrowes doe.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Now, what doth the Doue, but by his billing beget others, or the Sparrow, (but as the Cocke doth) by treading, ingender, bréede, and increaſe his own kind. And had the <hi>Phoenix</hi> a Phéere doe ſo with, ſhe would (in ſhort time) grow to this paſſe, to be neither ſo chaſt, nor ſo rare, as ſhe now is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioues</hi> armour bearer, the Eagle is euery way grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but no way ſo good as the Cocke is: for though he be the king of Birds, and therefore feared of all, yet he is a gréedy and a deuouring cormorant that prayes vpon them, and therefore beloued of none. Our Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons, and other ſwift winged Hawkes will ſore hye, and ſometimes delight vs a little: but the pleaſure and paſtime which they make vs is nothing in compariſon of that which our Cockes yéeld vs. And yet Hawking is a ſport of many great Perſonages, and braue ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted gentlemen, much vſed, and mightily accounted of,
<pb facs="tcp:12087:9"/> and to ſpeake as I thinke: it is a thing that deſerueth both to be loued, and commended: yet Cockes afford vs farre more pleaſure, than Hawkes can, though Hawkes be ten times more chargeable, and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and require ten times more attendance, than our Cockes doe.</p>
               <p>Then ſéeing our fighting Cockes are no whit inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the <hi>Phoenix</hi> for vertue, to the Eagle in goodneſſe, (though farre leſſe in greatneſſe) nor to Hawkes for mans commoditie, profit, and delectable pleaſure: but rather leſſe chargeable, and ten times more comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Surely we haue ſpeciall cauſe, both to be mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted to them, and alſo to make exceeding much of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> with a vaine oſtentation, boaſting of his owne ſtrength, told our Sauiour Chriſt in the Goſpel, that though all men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke him, yet he would not leaue him, but rather die with him: ſo proud was hée of his faith, and ſo prodigall of his loue. But Chriſt (who as he ſaith himſelfe, knew what was in man, and to how many infirmities fraile fleſh is ſubiect) ſaid vnto him; this night before the Cocke crow, thou ſhalt denie me thriſe; and as he ſaid it came to paſſe: for before the cocke crew, he both denied him, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſware him, ſaying, he knew not the man: but ſo ſoone as the Cocke did crow, it came immediatly into his mind, what his maſter had ſaid, and then inſtantly (as the text ſayth) he went out and wept betterly. Thus you may ſée it verified out of our Sauiours owne
<pb facs="tcp:12087:10"/> mouth, that the crowing of Cockes was ſeriouſly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and duely obſerued in his time, and alſo that the voice of the Cocke was (by Chriſts inſtitution) ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (like the voice of a Preacher) to call <hi>Peter</hi> to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to induce him to powre forth teares out of his eyes, to pacifie the wrath of God, for his haynous offence..</p>
               <p>What an vnſpeakable comfort was that Cocke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Noah,</hi> which in the time of the deluge, ſuruiued with him in the Arke, whoſe ſhril-tongued farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſounding voice (when he crowed) was heard by all the people in the world, at one inſtant. And what an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable comfort are Cockes continually vnto vs, for in all Countreys they are the Farmers clocks, who duely and truely declare vnto them, how the night paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and when the day light appeareth: and for this cauſe did the Swath-rutters make great account of Cockes, for when they were enticed, and procured to come into England in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion time, their wiues came with them, and brought their Cockes at their backes, which manifeſted an intire affection that they bare vnto them, when they chooſe rather to bring them with them, than any other thing which they enioyed: if you read the Chronicles, you ſhall finde this to be moſt true. But what néede I to recite, or alleage any circumſtance of ſuch antiquitie, for approbation of my argument, when we our ſelues, by dayly experience, cannot chooſe but ſee and perceiue what excéeding great comfort and conſolation all men haue, or may haue by them.</p>
               <p>I remember that in my young time, I being in bed with an Vncle of mine a learned Miniſter and a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Profeſſor of the word of God, how that after mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, the Cocke crowed, whereat my Vncle awaked, and told me that the voice of the Cocke did put him in
<pb facs="tcp:12087:10"/> mind of the paſſion of our Sauiour Chriſt, and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly hee fell to moſt earneſt praying. Likewiſe a man of good worſhip credibly informed me, that hée knew a Gentleman, that had many good Cockes of the game which he loued maruailouſly well, and wherein he tooke great felicitie and delight all his life time; and at the laſt falling into a gréeuous ſickneſſe, and lying vpon his death-bed, he requeſted his kinred and friends which were about him, to place his Cockes with their Coopes ſo néere vnto his beds head as poſſibly they could doe, which being performed according to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, he heard them crowe; whereat he ſayd, now haue I obtained that which I deſired; for theſe dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable voices ſhalbe my ſwéete-ſounding trumpets, to admoniſh and put me in minde of my immortall, and celeſtiall Iudge, before whome all fleſh muſt appeare, to receiue recompence according to their demerits, whether they be good or euill.</p>
               <p>Alſo our late Prince of famous memorie King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the Eight, did take ſuch pleaſure and wonderfull delight in the Cocks of the game, that he cauſed a moſt ſumptuous, and ſtately Cock-pit to be erected in <hi>Weſt-minſter,</hi> wherein his Maieſtie might diſport himſelfe with Cocke-fighting, among his moſt noble and louing ſubiects, who in like manner did affect that paſtime ſo well, and conceiued ſo good an opinion of it, not onely becauſe the King was ſo addicted to it, but alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the great valor and incomparable courage that the Cockes ſhewed in their battels; the which did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame their hearts, that they cauſed Cocke-pits to be made in many Citties, Boroughes, and Townes throughout the whole Realme. To which Cocke-pits reſorted, both Dukes, Earles, Lords, Knights, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and Yeomen, there to recreate and delight themſelues with Cocke-fighting,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12087:11"/>
               <p>Now this is to be noted that in this pleaſant exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe there is no colluſion, deceit, fraude, or cozening tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, nor any vſed (as in moſt other games, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cuſtomarily there is,) neither is there any braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or quarrels ſuffered in thoſe places: but all men, muſt there vſe ciuile and good behauiour, what degrée or calling ſoeuer he be of. And alſo it is there decréed vpon, and ſet downe as an irreuocable order, that no man by curſing banning, or ſwearing, ſhall blaſpheme God, or take his name in vaine, but that all of them ſhall ſpeake modeſtly, and deale according to truth and whoſoeuer ſhall diſcent from it, or do otherwiſe than is appointed, muſt vndergoe the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t preſcribed by the Nobilitie aforeſaid: which lawes then inſtituted &amp; ordayned, are yet to be ſéen extant, both in <hi>Suffolke</hi> and <hi>Norffolke,</hi> and I hope wil ſtill remaine and continue to the end of the world; which good obſeruation, hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced many to keepe Cockes of the game, and I doubt not but that in time, it will incite a number more, both to bréede them, and bring them vp, to the intent, that they may haue ſport with them to content and delight themſelues: for this is moſt certaine, that if euer any thing in the world were delectable, and pleaſant to the heart of man, and did beget in him any mirthfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance and conſolation, it was, and is the excellent ſport of Cocke fighting (as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> hath ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.) And this propertie or hidden miſterie, it hath in it; that whoſoeuer doth affect it, or (as diuers good men are) be much addicted to it, and then afterwards, either of his owne accord, or by any other mans inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or perſwaſion, doe neglect it, and refraine it, let him expect and looke for no other thing, but alwayes to be melancholy, ſad, and diſconſolate, and deſirous to wander alone, euer muſing on the worſt things, and not of the beſt: but rather imagining euill, than good.
<pb facs="tcp:12087:11"/> And this I know by experience, prooued by many men of good account, to their hinderance and griefe, and to my excéeding great ſorrow: and therefore I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh, aduiſe, and counſell all men, that take delight and pleaſure, in that delicious and pleaſant paſtime, neuer to forſake or leaue it, or to alienate themſelues from it, ſo long as it ſhall pleaſe the almightie to bleſſe and proſper them; for that which I haue here rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is neither fable, nor fiction, but an vndoubted truth and a thing that is moſt certaine: wherefore I for mine owne part, am thus reſolued ſo long as life and health laſt, and God lend my limbes abilitie, and ſtrength to beare me. I will neuer abſtaine from it, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently I may be at it, nor neuer conſent to giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that heart-pleaſing paſtime.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter. IIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Flammius</hi> the Grecian in a ſet bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, had ouerthrowne and ſpoyled a huge army, which the world-ſubduing <hi>Macedon</hi> brought thether: It is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for a moſt certaine truth, that hée and his company for ioy of that vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Victorie, ſhowted ſo loude, and ſo long together, that the clamorous noiſe of their exclamation ſéemed to ſhake the foundations of the earth, and ſo deaſened the eares of all creatures that came within the ſound ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that the fowles of the ayre, were thereby inforced to fall downe to the earth, and there lay (as it were in a traunce) being amazed, and aſtonied at the noyſe of their ayre-filling clamors. At which inſtant, euen in the middeſt of their excéeding great out-cry: It is ſaid that their Cockes (whereof they had aboundance) clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:12087:12"/> their winges, and crowed ſo often and ſo chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, with ſuch alacritie of ſpirite, as if they had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipated, or had a fellow-féeling of that ſoule-rauiſhing ioy, which was in their Maiſters: wherevpon <hi>Caly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> ſayd, that he had rather heare Cockes crowe, than muſicke ſound: for (ſaith he) the one cannot ſo much content my minde, as the other doth comfort my heart.</p>
               <p>Who would thinke that the crowing of a Cocke ſhould make a Lion quake? and yet it doth ſo, which is a moſt ſtrange &amp; a miraculous thing, that he, which is the King of beaſts, of whome it is ſaid, that the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his voice, will ingender feare in all the beaſts in the Forreſt, and make them tremble at the terrour of it, ſhould himſelfe tremble and be terrified (like a faint-hearted and a timorous-flying hare) with the ſound of a ſilly Cockes voice, yet of a truth it is, for of all thinges in the world, he cannot abide to heare a Cocke crowe; whereey we may moſt apparantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, the omnipotent power of the Almightie, who by the ſmalleſt creatures, can curbe, and controule the greateſt: as he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> by lice, and by the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt confound the ſtrongeſt, as he did <hi>Holofernes</hi> by the hand of <hi>Iudith; Siſera,</hi> by <hi>Iaell;</hi> and great <hi>Goliah</hi> by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Dauid.</hi> We may read in the 48 Chapter of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> that the Lord God, in that place com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth the Prophet to cry aloude, and ſpare not to lift vp his voyce like a Trumpet, and for this cauſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to tell the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> their ſinnes, and Iſraell their offences.</p>
               <p>Now what is it for a Preacher to eleuate, and lift vp his voice, but (as the Cocke doth) to rowze vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and clap his wings, that is, to ſhake of all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſloath, and negligence in himſelfe, and then to cry aloude vnto others chéerefully, to vtter his voice
<pb facs="tcp:12087:12"/> with vehemencie of ſpirite, and to deliuer his meſſage manfully, boldly, and with a good courage; as the Cocke did, when hée crowed néere to <hi>Caiphas</hi> houſe. Thus you ſée that of Cockes wee may learne many good leſſons, whereof we might make profitable vſes if we would rightly apply them vnto our ſelues: As firſt, to be conſtant and louing to our wiues, as they are to their Hens. Secondly, to be valorous and to fight cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly againſt our enemies, and (as they doe) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer giue ouer, but either get the victorie, or elſe die va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly. Thirdly, to be vigilant, and watchfull (as they are) and to auoide ſlouthfulneſſe, which generally raignes too much in vs. And laſtly, to ſtretch forth our ſelues, and to ſtraine our voyces in the vttering of Gods affaires.</p>
               <p>The bleſſed Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> the 6 Chapter, and the 12 verſe, chargeth <hi>Timothie</hi> to fight, the good fight of Faith, (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in him exhorteth all Chriſtians to do the ſame) whereupon one (interpreting the ſame text) ſaith thus: as the Cocke of the game, hauing receiued a hurt, or a wound from his aduerſarie, doth ſtraight wayes cloſe, and fight with him, vntill he hath ouercome him, or els be killed by him: ſo we being often ſtricken, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly wounded by the ſlye inſinuating blowes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than (our old and continuall aduerſarie) ſhould with the ſword of the ſpirit fight couragiouſly againſt all his aſſaults and temptations, vntill (by faith and prayers) we haue ouercome them, or by the power and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God be deliuered from them.</p>
               <p>Another thing now commeth into my minde, which I noted in the diſputation, betweene Maiſter <hi>Bannes</hi> and <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> Maiſter <hi>Barnes</hi> preaching in <hi>London</hi> at <hi>Paules</hi> Croſſe, compared himſelfe to a Cocke of the game, and <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> to another; but
<pb facs="tcp:12087:13"/> (quoth he) <hi>Stephen</hi> hath no ſpurres, ſignifying thereby, that (in his opinion) <hi>Gardiner</hi> was not ſo well armed at all points, to endanger and offend his aduerſarie as himſelfe was. Furthermore, it is growne to be a cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome here amongſt vs in this Realme of <hi>England,</hi> that when we haue any troubles, ſuits in law, or cauſes of weight in hand, our eſpeciall friend demanding of vs, if we haue not ſolicited and made means to ſuch a man to be a Mediator for vs, or to be friend vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, we moſt commonly will make them this anſwere, I haue made that Cocke-ſure; ſo rare, ſinguler, and ſo excellent a creature is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cocke, that diuers good things haue relation vnto him, and euen a multitude of things might be ſpoken of him.</p>
               <p>I remember I once heard a Yorke-ſhire man (that dwelleth néere to the borders of <hi>Scotland</hi>) ſay, that he would not giue a Cocke of the game, which he had in his Coope at home, for halfe the Cowes the beſt man in their Towne had in his milking-yard. Many more things I could repeat, and alleage for the credite and commendation of the Cockes of the game: but thoſe that are alreadie rehearſed, may ſerue for a ſufficient probabilitie of their vertues, courage, and excellent qualities, without any further recitals, or more teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; wherefore I will now proceede, and explaine vnto you the diſtinction, and difference, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them &amp; other Cockes: and withall make a briefe repetition of ſome ſtrange and moſt admirable battels, which my ſelfe haue ſeene, in diuers and ſundry places at Cocke-fightings, to the great contentation, both of my ſelfe and many others: and therewithall conclude, and knit vp this little Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:12087:13"/>
               <head>Chapter. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here bée ſome men which will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with themſelues and ſay: we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and maruaile much, why theſe people bée ſo zealouſly affected, and ſo much in loue with the Cockes of the game, more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with any other Cocks, imagining with themſelues, yea, and perſwading their owne hearts, that their Cockes of the Dung-hill, are as good in euerie degrée, as they are, and make them as much paſtime as they can. But beléeue me, my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt friends, it is neither ſo, nor ſo; for there be diuers and ſundry kindes and ſorts of Cockes, but for breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſake, I will onely intreat but of thrée ſorts, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall kinds: that is, the Cockes of the game, the halfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Cockes, and the Dung-hill, or crauen Cockes. The Cockes of the game are ſo called, becauſe they carrie the credite away from all other Cockes in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, which is the onely cauſe they are ſo highly eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſo much valued as they be; for it is generally and commonly ſéene, that the moſt heroycall and noble hearted men, take greateſt delight in thoſe thinges which are of moſt courage, and greateſt valour, and that of all others (in my opinion) is the Cockes of the game: as already I haue ſufficiently declared. But as for your crauen Cockes, the beſt and chiefeſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, that they will or can make you is, when they are well boyled, or ſtewed, and layde in a platter with good ſtore of plumbes about them, and then you may aſſure your ſelues they will not ſhrinke for a blow, but otherwiſe let them be well matched, and cloſe coupled to Cockes of the game, and I dare aſſure you, they wil
<pb facs="tcp:12087:14"/> quickely take their leaue of them, and in moſt coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and baſe manner runne away from them, to your great griefe and diſcontentment. Yet notwithſtanding all this, there be ſome ſimple men, which will report and ſay thus of them, they ſerue our turnes wel inough to crow, and to tread our Hens. Well, I graunt, and beleeue they doe ſo, and that is the greateſt valour or vertue that is in them; but to compare them with the Cockes of the game, you miſtake your marke, and are more than much deceiued, for there is no compariſon to be made of or betwixt them, nor any indifferent equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in them: for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayth in the Booke of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that God in the creation made all thinges perfect, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely good, and in their right kinde, but moſt of your Cockes (by groſſe and irregular bréeding) are become imperfect, and ſo conſequently prooue crauins, and cowardly minded fowles: and in that manner will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, and continue in diſpight of you, doe what you can to helpe it, which cauſeth all men that breed Cocks. (if either they loue them, or deſire to haue any paſtime with them) to eſchew and auoide them, as much as poſſibly in them lyeth: for what man amongſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand (if he haue any ſparke of wiſedome knowledge, or vnderſtanding in him) that doth bréed, kéepe, or nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh vp any creature whatſoeuer, but will deſire to bring vp that which of it ſelfe is moſt abſolute, and of the perfecteſt kinde, and beſt breede that can or may be gotten, or procured? Now laſtly, as concerning your halfe-bred cockes, which are ingendred by the cocke of the game, and of the crauen Hen, or by the right bred, and beſt qualified Hen, and of the Dung-hill and degenerate cocke: what will they doe but euen when you expect, and hope for beſt of them, and (ſéeing them fight) thinke the battell to bee ſurely wonne on their ſides, deceiue your expectation, and fruſtrate your
<pb facs="tcp:12087:14"/> hopes, for if one of them, doe but chance to looſe an eie, or receiues any hurt, or damage that ſeemes to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to him, then God be with your game, for he is gone, the houſe is too hot, the fight too fierce, and the danger too great for him to endure it. Therefore I doe ſtil magnifie, and extoll the cockes of the game, becauſe their courage can neuer be quayled, nor their hearts daunted by any wound, or hurt, how déepe ſoeuer it be indented. For confirmation and proofe whereof, I will ſhew you an inſtance.</p>
               <p>There was a cocke about Shroue-tide laſt, which in the cocke-pit in the citie of <hi>Norwich,</hi> fought with a ſtronge, and a ſtout aduerſarie, vntill ſuch time as both his eyes were beaten out, his head ſore wounded, and ſhrewdly battered, and all his bodie moſt pitifully bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and then with the ſudden aſtoniſhment of a ſound blow, which from his cruell aduerſarie he receiued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaten downe, and lying for dead, not ſtirring any whit, nor ſéeming otherwiſe (to the beholders) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſtarke dead, he ſuddenly ſtarted vp, contrary to all their expectations, (when there was offered twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, yea, twenty pounds to be layd to one, that there was no breath remayning in his bodie and cloſed with his aduerſarie, at whom he ſtroke moſt violent blowes, and neuer gaue ouer, vntill (to the amazement of all the ſpectators) hee had moſt valiantly ſlaine him. Oh ſtrange action oh ſtout heart, and vndaunted minde, who would imagine ſuch great courage ſhould bee in ſo ſmall a creature, or almoſt beléeue (but that their eies may dayly behold, and ſee it) that ſuch dreadleſſe feare, ſcorning valour, ſhould remaine in a cocke. Tell me (I pray) you that make as much account of a ſqeaking Caſtrell, or a ſcuruie Hobbie, as you doe of a good Hawke? you that thinke euerie Dunghill crauen, to be as good as a cocke of the game; tell me (I ſay) when
<pb facs="tcp:12087:15"/> did you euer ſée any of your baſe-bred Cockes ſhewe ſuch courage, or doe ſuch an admirable action? ſurely neuer, neither ſhall you euer knowe any of them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the like. Thus you may ſée by this one inſtance, that they are not ſo good, as the other are, but farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to them: and therefore who (but rough hewen clownes, and ruſticke <hi>Corridons</hi>) would bréede and bring vp crauens, when he may haue of the right kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt many other Battels fought, and diuers great exployts done by Cockes of the game in ſundry places, giue me a little leaue (I pray) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port vnto you, what credite a Cocke of mine owne bréeding (whome I called <hi>Iipſey</hi>) wonne at Saint <hi>Edmunds-Burie</hi> in <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke,</hi> where he plaid his prize ſo excellently, and fought ſo couragiouſly, that after many admirable, and almoſt incredible acts atchieued by him, diuers Gentlemen &amp; my verie good friends, in commendation of him cauſed his picture to be drawn &amp; painted vpon a cloth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon theſe, or the like words were written.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O noble <hi>Iipſey,</hi> ſuch a Cocke art thou,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Burie</hi> Towne, did nere containe till now.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore to praiſe thy worth and ſpread thy fame,</l>
                  <l>We make this ſhewe in honour of thy name.</l>
               </q>
               <p>So ſoone as the painted cloth was thus finiſhed, the cocke was put into a prettie fine cage, which two men carried betwixt them, the cloth being borne a good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb facs="tcp:12087:15"/> before them, and in this manner hauing the waights of the Towne with vs, the trayned Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Cocke-maſters, and diuers others: we marched too and fro, throughout the whole towne: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, we returned to the Cocke-pit againe, where the Cocke was no ſooner ſet downe, but all the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers diſcharged their péeces ouer him, which we thought would haue daunted &amp; diſcoraged him for euer: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the noyſe they made, he was nothing diſmaide, but in the verie middle of the volley of ſhot, he clapped his wings and crowned, which was as much valour, as I, or I thinke any of the companie euer ſaw in a Cocke. I doe aſſure you this is moſt certaine, and the ſaid Towne and Countie will auouch the ſame.</p>
               <p>Alſo no longer agoe, than the 4 day of May 1602, at a Cocke-fighting in the Citie of <hi>Norwich</hi> aforeſayd, a Cocke called <hi>Tarlecon</hi> (who was ſo intituled, becauſe he alwayes came to the fight like a Drummer, making a thundering noyſe with his winges) which Cocke ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing there fought many battels, with mighty and fierce Aduerſaries: and being both wearied with long figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and alſo verie hardly matched, at the length he had his eyes both of them beaten out of his head, his ſpurres broken off, and his bill bruſed, and rigorouſly rent from off his face, ſo that their remained no hope of him, but that he ſhould bee inſtantly killed, and ſo of neceſſitie looſe all the wagers that he fought for, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a rare and miraculous wonder, a moſt admirable ſeldome or neuer ſeene accident; for all this he fought ſtill moſt ſtoutly with his Aduerſary, and would neuer ſhrinke from him, or giue him ouer, vntil he had (which to all men there preſent ſéemed to be an impoſſibilitie) moſt couragiouſly ſlaine him. Oh ineſtimable ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe! oh inuincible valour! oh miraculous magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie! oh more than Lion-hearted fowles! who doth great
<pb facs="tcp:12087:16"/> not admire at their vndaunted and naught-dreading mindes: or who hath euer ſéene, or heard, or read of ſo great courage in any liuing creatures in the world, as is in them. Whhat is he, or where liues he (that beares the true minde of a man, that would not loue them, feed them, cheriſh them, and make much of them, if they did vnderſtand, and know the manifold vertues, and excéeding great valor that is in them? man neuer kept, the world neuer bred, the earth neuer bare more exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and worthy to be beloued creatures, than Cockes are. Many more commendations, than I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed may be giuen vnto them, and many farre more excellent things might be ſpoken of them, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their nature, nurture, vertues, qualities, and courage, than either I haue expreſſed, or am any way able to expreſſe ſufficiently: Wherefore I am reſolued to leaue that Herculean taſke, for ſome more bleſſed brain to take in hand: and onely content my ſelfe with that, which I haue already done, not doubting, but that in time, this illiterate and imperfect Embrion, will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate and allure ſome of <hi>Apolloes</hi> ſacred heires, ſome of <hi>Thamiſis</hi> ſwéet ſinging Swans, ſome heauen-inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſoule-enchanting Poet, to carroll forth at full, in high and heart-pleaſing ſtraines, their due and well deſerued praiſes: which thing I would be moſt glad of, and will hartily pray for.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12087:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
